So, we're going to start the actual uh
Lamrim and I was working on it
yesterday.
And uh
I was studying when did we start it? In
case you're curious.
Uh
I found a record, Rob. We started on the
last day of 2010.
Uh December 31st, 2010. Yeah, in
Prescott.
And
uh
I actually Anyway, okay.
Uh the first class was December 31st. Uh
and um
so there are 24
original days of teaching uh in the
original teaching.
And uh we did
21st,
2nd, 3rd and
Sorry.
Yeah, we did 21, 22, 23, 24. We finished
the
meditation part and we finished the
emptiness part.
And then we started uh at the beginning
and started to go through the Lamrim.
And we're about to hit the last day.
Okay? We're about to start the last day,
uh which is like 22 or something like
that.
Uh
and we've done 46 retreats
uh in 14
in 14 years. Yeah.
Cool.
And uh
I was checking to see if uh
if we went to some compass,
famous book on emptiness, instead of
doing more Lamrim
on emptiness.
Uh I was checking to see if it would
take much longer.
And
uh
they're about the same
length. Okay. So, if we do emptiness
from the Lamrim Chamou, the big Lamrim,
or we do emptiness from his famous
teaching on
uh Nagarjuna and Chandrakirti, it will
take about the same
time.
Which is 9 years.
Okay.
So,
then uh
So, I thought you could come to the
nursing home
and uh
visit me and
uh
it's about um
Yeah, so I don't know if if you're up
for an I'm okay.
YEAH, OKAY.
OKAY.
UH
THAT BOOK IS A commentary on
Chandrakirti,
who lived about 1,300 years ago,
and he wrote a book called
Entering the Middle Way,
Madhyamakavatara.
And in this case, Middle Way is a
nickname for a book. Yeah, it's the root
text of Nagarjuna.
And it's his most famous book
called uh
in sometimes it's just called Wisdom.
And people have made the name longer,
and I think Nagarjuna didn't want them
to make the name longer. He was very
He was like a rap artist or something.
And now, his poetry is very, very
beautiful, very short, and very
mystical,
and very deep. And so, and we've been
doing
another commentary by Tony Lama
in the fall. We've been reading
Tony Lama's commentary to Nagarjuna.
So, I thought uh we could just keep
doing that kind of thing. It's like a
potent
When you get cancer really bad, they
start injecting stuff into you every
morning.
A mix of stuff. Like you get cocaine,
morphine.
It's like that.
So, you'll get uh an injection every
couple times a year.
And uh
I think it'd be nice. So, we can keep
going through We're almost done with
Tony Lama.
Uh
on the original root text of Nagarjuna.
And then we'll do Chandrakirti.
Uh
so, his Entering the Middle Way is
Entering Wisdom, the book called Wisdom.
So, when they say Middle Way, in that
case, it means the book called Wisdom,
Prajnaparamita.
By Arya Nagarjuna, which is probably the
greatest book on emptiness
ever written. Chandrakirti is the second
greatest book.
And Shantideva is the third greatest
book. So, you're going to get all three.
Uh
and uh I think it's awesome. I think
it'd be fun.
Uh
and I'd like to do that.
So, you actually don't have a choice.
Okay.
Uh
and we'll just see how far we get.
Okay. Uh so, I'm going to pick up
in the in the Lamrim of Pabongka
Rinpoche. And uh
There's a deep uh connection with
Lojong.
So, Pabongka Rinpoche's
Uh there's a person who was recording
his teaching, and that was
Trijang Rinpoche, Kyabje Kyabje Trijang
Rinpoche, who who's Junior Tutor of the
Dalai Lama and he's the teacher of my
teacher.
Uh so uh
this book that we're studying now,
I think it's the greatest book ever
written in Tibetan.
Uh and Tibetan language has now been
destroyed.
Uh
so I don't think there will be any more
books uh
of this quality. The the language has
been uh destroyed.
So people Nobody speaks Tibetan anymore
uh except me.
Uh
that's kind of funny.
I was in uh
Geshe Lotar was doing a long life prayer
for me here
and I got a gallbladder attack.
And he and I was lying on the floor
in great pain and I said, "Geshe Lotar,
I got to go to the the hospital, which
is 2 hours away." And he's like, "Just
wait. I want to finish your long life
prayer."
And I said, "I'm going to be the first
person in history to die during their
long life prayer."
And uh and uh
it was really cute.
Then I went to uh they took me to the
hospital and I had an operation and
when I woke up from the
what do you call it?
the drugs and I I looked and there's a
Tibetan woman leaning over me, you know.
And I'm like, "Wow, you know."
And uh
I said uh
"What's your name?"
And she said, "I'm Tsering." Which means
long life.
And that's the name of the dog of in the
How Yoga Works, right?
So I'm like, "Of course your name is
Tsering, you know."
And
And then
I said, "Who are you?" And she said,
"I'm your doctor." I said, "Of course,
yeah."
And uh
And I said, "How many Tibetans are in
Tucson?" She said, "Two."
And I'm like, of course, you know. And
so we were, you know, she was telling me
we started talking in Tibetan and she
says, "You have a perfect Lhasa accent.
And they don't exist anymore. Nobody
Nobody can speak it anymore. It's It's
dead.
You know, in in
in some countries it sounds like one
language and in another country it
sounds like a different language.
But nobody speaks pure Tibetan anymore.
And
so that book you're studying today
it is the greatest book ever written in
Tibetan and it's probably the last one
ever written in pure Tibetan. So
it's a beautiful the the writing
is extraordinary. And so
if you're interested in Tibetan, it's a
good book to learn Tibetan. Okay.
And Wordsmith has been teaching some
wonderful classes.
I don't know how he teaches Tibetan
but the people who study with him learn
faster and better than my students.
So
if you're interested
you know, these classes are free a
couple times a week and
you can learn. It's beautiful.
I I encourage people to read Tibetan. Um
you can learn Sanskrit. I learned
Sanskrit. It took 12 years.
With a great scholar and I don't use it.
I have never used it.
Cuz 90
99% of the books were destroyed
in India around uh
800 AD. So there's not You can learn
Sanskrit but there's no Sanskrit to
read.
Uh Uh, it's mostly gone.
We're studying a little bit in the
mixed nuts in the Shen Sang Tower
classes. If you're interested, those are
Sages' new classes.
Uh,
on the Guide to the Bodhisattva's Way of
Life, which is a really
good way to learn Sanskrit. It's
excellent Sanskrit by Shantideva. So, we
do have that Sanskrit.
And I've been teaching that Sanskrit and
Christina Casica, where are you?
She's been uh, leading a class
in Sanskrit
after that every every week, I guess.
Starting in June
of this year?
Okay.
Uh,
but she's Harvard-trained
Sanskrit person, so
you know, not as good as Princeton, but
it's okay.
And uh,
all right. Uh,
so
this is like the great So, I'm going to
read the Tibetan just to get it into
your brain.
We only have one more day
out of the 24-day original teaching. I
average uh,
two retreats per day.
So, uh, we can finish probably this
year, Tim, I don't know. And then we can
go to uh,
some campus book on emptiness, okay? And
I personally, as you may have noticed,
I'm not in any big rush.
I just enjoyed
reading it together and uh,
so just relax and enjoy.
The nice thing about Lamrim, you don't
have to study.
Uh, you just have to be open and uh,
it will get into you whether you want it
or not.
Okay. All right.
And I'm going to use some items. Items
are pictures
uh, to remember the ideas of the book.
So, I I have
pictures that help you remember the
points in the book, okay?
I call them idea images, which are and I
it it not idiot, idiom.
Okay? All right.
So, here we go and uh
Tim, you got you guys got the Tibetan up
there?
Okay, good. Uh
Lama lama good on lojong lochog don ten
shiki lo ja so ma so nyam ma men pa cha.
Lama lama good means
uh keep up your affection for your
teacher.
Okay? And um
you know, I've been in the Dharma
business for 50 years and uh
I've seen all kinds of students,
thousands, and uh
some are pain in the ass.
And they're always like, "Oh, Lama Lama,
you know?" And then they don't know how
to wash dishes.
Uh
and then there's other students who are
just like, "Hi, Geshe Michael. Let's
let's do something cool."
And they do wash dishes and uh
so I I kind of prefer that kind, and I
think it's healthier
than this uh
you know, super prostration thing.
And uh
I'd much rather have my dishes washed
than get another tired roast.
Okay, but both are okay.
All right.
And uh no, you should you should offer
things, but small things. I don't need
money, I don't need things, okay? I got
so many things in my house. I have
it's trouble for me to keep them out of
my house, so
uh
but uh
serving at Diamond Mountain, helping
here and that's great, stuff like that.
That's great.
Uh Lama Lama good so have a nice
relationship with your teacher, fun
relationship.
Uh
you know,
the reason you have a teacher is you're
bad.
Okay?
So, don't be disappointed if you
if you don't act nice to your teacher,
okay? It's normal.
Okay? If you didn't act bad toward your
teacher, you wouldn't need a teacher.
You understand?
So, uh
don't don't get all
It's It's one thing to be bad to your
teacher. It's another thing to feel bad
that you're bad.
And
at least just feel good about it.
And uh
you're okay. You're okay. That's what
So, no student can ever really serve
their teacher properly, or else they
wouldn't need a teacher. You see what I
mean? So, just do your best
and have fun, and you'll do a lot
better, okay?
Lojong like tool. And by the way,
everybody has a big mess-up, can I say?
And don't worry about that, either,
okay? In their life in their Dharma
life, you will have two or three
very special mess-ups.
And don't worry about that Don't worry
about that, either, okay? We We all have
had
special mess-ups, okay? And just
you can brag about it in the hell
realms.
Uh
My teacher was giving us uh
diamond way vows. It was in Alexandria,
Virginia, I remember, in this wealthy
lady's house.
First of all, the lady offered him the
house.
And he He looked at me, and I'm like,
And uh
we can sell it, you know. And and
then he's like, "Nah, you keep it, you
know. I don't need a house."
And then
we were making dinner together and
cutting stuff and vegetables. And And
then she said uh
so you're giving us
diamond way vows today.
And he said, "Yep, that's what we're
doing." And and she said, "Well,
I heard something about that." And he
said, "What?" And and she said, "I heard
if you break those vows, you go to the
lowest hell."
You know, and he said, "That's true."
And she says, "Well, wouldn't it be
better to
not take the vows and not go to the
lowest hell?"
And he says, "Oh, you're going to the
lowest hell anyway.
Everybody is, you know."
And then she's like she she had this
look on her face. She was a professor
somewhere.
I won't say more cuz you'll figure out
who she is. Um
then she's like
and then he says,
"Yeah, when you go to hell and you meet
everybody else who's there,
you can say, 'I'm not here
just cuz I killed people or stole
things.
I'm here cuz I broke my diamond way
vows.'
You know."
Anyway,
uh so have fun with the lojong.
Uh Tashi Gyaltsen means
you know, try to remember what you hear
in the class and it it's nice here
during retreat
cuz you can tell everyone's trying to
control themselves
after class.
Uh
like at the cafeteria, everybody's like,
"You take first."
You know, and
then, you know, you get on the plane and
you forget everything you said.
Uh
but try your best
to
you know, take what you hear and then go
use it in the cafeteria.
And see if it survives the drive to
Tucson.
All right. Uh so what's up? Nyima Tenzin
Pema Yeshe focus on these three things.
Have fun with your llama,
enjoy the lojong, and try to remember
when you get home. Okay, that's all.
And okay, then he says and did you show
that picture of the lady I guess? I
don't know.
Yeah, that just means enjoy the meal,
okay? Enjoy the class. Enjoy the lojong.
You know, enjoy the taste and don't get
too serious on me, okay?
It's
I've noticed the very serious people
usually fail.
Okay, so just relax. If you can laugh at
yourself, you're you're halfway there,
okay?
And you are funny. Okay.
All right, next picture you guys.
Yeah, this represents your three doors.
What are they you guys for zero dollars?
Body, speech, and mind, yeah.
I told Aldo he looked more wealthy this
morning.
So, he's probably taking people out to
dinner for the next couple weeks. So,
in Colorado, huh? Right?
He says Nunga Yid Sum Telwar Mashagpa
Gewalakpo.
Telwar Mashagpa means you were given
a body, a mouth, and a mind when you
entered this life. Use them.
Okay, use them. And these are called the
three doors. These are the only way you
can express yourself, okay? You can do
things for other people with your hands.
You can say things to other people with
your mouth.
And most importantly, you can think
things about other people. So, you He
says
Telwar Mashagpa. This is the Tel that
you find in Teljor. What's that?
Yeah, leisure and and So, Tel here means
leisurely and it means uh
don't let your body, speech, and mind
just sit there, use them.
Okay? So, that this del doesn't quite
mean the same as leisure and fortune. It
means
I'm slowing down translators. I can see
you're stressed out, okay?
That's a good idea to put them here in
front of me.
Sorry about that.
Uh yeah, del warmashaka means don't
don't let them just sit there, use them.
You were born with a body and a and you
were hands and you were born with a
mouth and you were born with a brain, so
use it.
What? Gewal aku. Ku means uh
to take. Did you ever work with donkeys?
Re- I mean real donkeys, not
So, I was a boy scout in in Arizona in a
mountains like this and uh we
had mules and uh
we had to load them up and take them on
five
day hikes and stuff and they are
really stubborn.
And
and you can't stand behind them cuz
they'll kick you
and uh break your leg
and they just won't move, you know? You
you whip them, you beat them, you yell
at them, they're like, "Hm?"
And remind me of a lot of students I
met.
Uh
so,
don't let your mind and body just sit
there, you know? Say, "Come on, let's
let's let's wash dishes this morning."
Your and your body will be, "I don't
know."
You know? And
ku ku means uh
I don't know. Get it get it to do
something. Ta- Get the donkey to do
something, okay? All right.
Lukyi gewani chakor sokyang ba mingyi.
This is a beautiful sentence and
and I don't know how long it took
Tsongkhapa to write
this lecture down.
And I'm not sure the lecture was as good
as the writing.
Um,
but uh
it must have taken him 10 or 15 years.
And and that's why
I think he was made the teacher of the
Dalai Lama. That's why he was given that
position.
Because it was so amazing. That the book
he wrote down was so amazing.
Uh and here's a typical
you know, we call one-liner in English.
It's like a single sentence that you can
carry for the rest of your life, okay?
Uh lü kyi gewa ni chos khor so kyang ma
yin
uh
physical good deeds with your body, it's
not restricted to chos khor. And khor uh
chos sel
and ney ten khorwa. Uh chos sel means
prostration.
And khorwa means to walk around uh a
holy place, okay? That's tradition.
We we should walk around these stupas,
okay?
People like, "What's a stupa for?" I
said, "Nothing."
They're like, "Huh?"
Well, you can walk around it, okay? And
it's a good custom.
Okay? So
uh he says
good physical karma is not limited to
prostrations and walking around holy
places. Rather, kyi, okay? Uh tim at the
end of a a phrase, it means but or
rather, right? Rather, lü dug lü chos
khor so ma yin kyang
uh if you talk about virtue or good
deeds of the first of your three doors
of expression, which is your
physical body, he says sitting up
straight is a good deed of physical
body.
Because your prana will move. Your prana
will move better. Okay? It's very
interesting. Everybody's like
I knew it was coming so I sat up before.
Uh
tsomo sang so tsomo sang means uh
just being mindful of how you sit
especially that you don't do this thing.
I have a friend from Rimrock, a new a
new friend from Rimrock
who tends to sit like that. You've got
to
you know, keep keep your back straight.
Uh
I like to sit on the edge of a chair. I
don't like to sit like you know, like
this. And then uh it'll help your prana.
And that helps your mind. Okay? It keeps
your mind more clear. So your practice
will be better if your posture is good.
Okay? And he says you don't have to be
prostrating
to do a physical good deed. You can just
sit up straight
and that's a physical good karma to sit
up straight and remember to sit up
straight
and uh
keep the prana moving smoothly.
And then you can focus better. Okay? Uh
and it's healthier. By the way, it's
easier if you don't if you're not
overweight.
It's hard to sit up straight if you're
overweight. So um
you know, we can talk about that
sometime.
Um but there's there's easy ways to not
get overweight and then you can
you can sit better. Okay?
All right.
Do look tsomo sang
sin here. Sin means uh
Sin means starting with that and then
going higher. Okay? Yeah, sin means
start with that. Luky gewa, that is a
good karma of physical body.
Uh
you don't have to give money.
You don't have to I don't know, save a
person in a car accident sitting up
straight
because you want your prana to flow
smoothly. It's already a good karma,
okay? And you can make good karma just
sitting there.
Which is
we need all the good karma we can get.
So, if you can make some extra good
karma just by sitting straight, then
let's go for it.
Okay.
All right.
Uh
next picture, you guys.
Yeah, and this is I don't know, this
part is really cool. He's heavy into
lojong. And by the way,
uh
Trijang Rinpoche
was big on lojong. And I was reading his
biography. He wrote a beautiful
biography.
And one of my teachers, uh Sherpa
Rinpoche who's in the Vajrayogini
lineage, Tenzin Tsering,
uh he translated it into English. Uh so,
if you if you have time,
it's a beautiful uh book. It's the
biography of Trijang Rinpoche. You can
read it on You can buy it on Amazon.
And uh
he he taught
uh
this lojong
uh several times in his life. He did
long long teachings
on on the lojong of Geshe's book, The
Crown of Lives.
And they're beautiful comments about it.
He made beautiful comments about it. He
was
he was in Tibet during the Red Guard
time. He saw a million people die.
And he was kind of in charge of the
government, or he was one of the top
people in the government. So, he he
watched a a million people die.
And he talks about it in lojong. He
says, you know,
we have to apply lojong to this. We
cannot hate other people.
Uh Uh, we have to we have to practice
lojong. And it's amazing that a person
who went through that
uh, who saw a million people die. I saw
some of those people.
You know, and it's amazing to to
to think that he wrote this uh, lojong.
He he wrote down that he was practicing
it
all day. He was struggling not to hate
people.
And uh, it's very powerful.
Lojong che yu dra dra da nyen she ri se
che pa don. He said,
"As soon as you distinguish between dra
and nyen, okay? What's dra chomba?"
Enemy destroy. Enemy destroyer, our
heart, right?
Uh, so dra means enemy and nyen means
friend. And he says, "As soon as you
distinguish between people you like
and people you don't like, your lojong
has failed."
Okay. As you know, if you're in the
lojong business, if you're in the lojong
business
and you can say, uh, "I prefer this
person to this person," you already
flung the lojong.
Okay.
Uh, and you know, we all do that and you
can't help it and I can't help it.
But we have to try, right? We have to
try. That's lojong. That's training the
mind. Sem jong. Sem jong.
Okay. So, uh, dona nyen she ri se
ri se che pa means to uh,
what do you call it?
Segregate or to what do you call it?
These my friends, these are my not my
friends.
Bias. All kinds of bias, right?
Prejudice
is uh, anti-lojong.
Okay. Mm.
Ri se che pa and
sem chen don sem chen mem pa la so pa.
Uh,
just between people who hurt you and
people who help you.
Lojong is for everybody, okay?
They take you tongue che la kaba no ting
ne jong wa che pa.
Che ka wa tar ga.
Tong you tongue che la kaba means
your lojong practice has to be
universal.
It has to cover all living things, okay?
Ting ne means from the bottom of your
heart.
Is the verb, okay?
Do your lojong.
Means jong eh, jong eh, get better at
it, keep practicing, okay? Jong by the
way, lojong jong
it implies two things. Number one,
you don't have it now.
So, you have to jong.
Got it? It means practice. So, you don't
have lojong naturally. People don't have
lojong naturally. It's something you
have to develop. And it's called
developing the good heart, right? That's
how we translate it in lojong.
You can call it mental training. I
object to that translation. I think it
sounds like uh
a prison camp where they're trying to
brainwash you. It sounds like
brainwashing someone.
It means to develop a good heart, okay?
Jong wa che pa.
Che ka wa tar ga. Che ka wa um lived
1101 to 1175. He was a famous
geshe, old time geshe.
Nowadays geshe is a degree title. In the
old days it meant
uh a great
personal master of somebody, okay?
And um
he's an interesting
geshe because uh
about
400 years
after lojong started, he let it out to
the public.
He opened it to the public. The lojong
dondoma, the seven point lojong, okay?
Which is what we're studying in this
long room.
Okay? And so he's special.
A special lojong practitioner. Why keep
it secret?
Peacocks. Good answer. Who said that?
Sometimes
sometimes I don't make a bet
and a person gives an answer that's
worth a bet. So $100.
YEAH.
YOU CAN TAKE ME OUT TO dinner on
Tuesday.
Okay.
Don't forget your teacher. Uh
Uh
Yeah, he's the one who who let out the
the lojong, okay?
Yeah, and if you
I like this peacock thing because um
because sometimes not sometimes I avoid
trouble. Like I there's a situation in
the organizations. We have 41
organizations.
Uh
and there's always trouble somewhere
sometime. The trouble rotates around
to different organizations, especially
financial.
And you know, grandpa follows the
trouble and
I like to avoid it. I like to say, you
know,
give me a break already, you know? Give
me 6 months off without fundraising.
You know? And I'm like
uh
But if you're a peacock
uh you're supposed to look for trouble
and you're supposed to follow it, you
know? So I I don't know. It's kind of a
curse.
You know, if you get in the lojong
business
uh you have to follow problems and you
have to look for problems and you have
to stand up
whenever there's a problem and you have
to say, "I'm here." Okay. Okay.
Put some more fundraising on this old
bald head.
You know.
And
you got to look for
problems and you got to step up. And
those are the poison that the peacock
eats. Okay. So, if you're going to be a
Lojong. By the way, don't decide
easily to be a Lojong practitioner. You
might want to say, "I'll do it next
life."
I promise, Geshe-la.
You know, look me up. Uh
so, uh
But, uh if you want to do it in this
life,
you got to be a peacock, you know. And
And I think uh
it's it's difficult. It's hard. It's
tiring.
You know. And every time you get on top
of it, there's one more problem.
And then, you know, you say, "Hey, I
learned how to deal with
300 people's problems." And then, 301
shows up.
And you're like, "Okay. Just
I'll take care of you, too." And then,
uh
I think you have to understand emptiness
to survive as a peacock.
Okay. Which means uh you have to
understand
that every problem you ever encounter is
coming from you.
Or you will break down. You won't be
able to handle all the problems. We had
a suicide yesterday in town here.
Uh young man that we were trying to
help.
And uh
stuff happens.
And
do your best. And you try hard.
And try to help help people.
And uh I think if you
don't understand that they are coming
from you,
uh you will break down. You know, you
won't be able to handle it. Okay, so
uh
I think if you're going to be in the
peacock business
uh
and you're trying to help all these
people, then uh you have to
understand
the pen.
And you have to understand that this
person came from you.
And that it's a reflection of you. And
uh if you understand that
then you can
then you don't run away from these
problems, you know. It would be easy to
ignore Bowie. It's so
eminently ignorable.
You know.
It's hard to even notice it when you're
driving in town.
If If If a lot of the buildings weren't
burned down, you wouldn't notice it.
Uh
and uh
but a peacock has to pause and stop and
and say, "What can I do? How can I
help?" You know, and then you don't
always succeed, okay?
And you can't give up being a peacock,
okay?
And uh
And those are the way to survive as a
peacock is to understand that it's
coming from you, okay? And that's the
only way.
And if people
haven't had that training about
emptiness
you should keep the lojong secret key
secret from them. You should not teach
them lojong cuz then they'll try to
help too many people and they'll break
down. And then they'll you know, they'll
be the next victims, okay?
The only way you can
keep up the
the demands of a peacock is to
understand that this stuff is coming
from you.
And therefore it's much easier to fix.
You don't have to fix all the messed up
people in the world.
Uh you have to just fix that one messed
up person.
Okay?
Which is more doable.
Okay.
Uh
let's see here. There's a photo of the
young man. Is he Is he here?
Uh, and if you'd like to pray for him,
his his name was Manny.
Okay.
Next picture.
Dynamite. Uh,
Uh, lama pama shakro tabula sut kunai
ting jongba
Jongba gom means I want you to practice
your lojong keep up your lojong
practice.
Uh, kepa means especially with dra.
With enemies, okay? Uh, what's the
Sanskrit for dra?
Ari, yeah. Ari. Who's that, Ari?
100.
I don't know if he's worth 100 dollars.
Okay, 100 dollars.
He usually takes people out to dinner
pretty easily. Um,
yeah, Ari means enemy in Sanskrit and
hot
uh, comes from the verbal root hun,
which means to kill.
Uh, so ara ari hun or ari hot arhat
means uh, enemy destroyer, okay?
Hun
Hun came into English as
gun in the word gun, okay?
Comes from the same root, hot hot.
Okay, so anyway,
uh,
your lojong practice, you have to
emphasize
your enemies, which means
I mean, practicing lojong is kind of
like uh, schizophrenia.
You know, you're like, "God, this person
really irritates me." Yeah. So, I should
spend more time around them. Oh, not
again, you know.
You know, you're like, can't we just do
lojong next month? You know,
do we have to? And you And then your
heart your heart is like,
yeah, we have to. Lojong is for enemies,
you know. You can't practice lojong if
you avoid your enemies.
Okay, you have to sit next to them in
the kitchen. And not I mean in the
cafeteria. Now we're seeing who sits
next to who.
Okay, so
just kidding.
So, my kid got one.
Uh so, it's difficult to be patient
towards your enemies. You learn nyam
bar.
Then he says people who are So, you have
to be especially careful in lojong
karmically
with people you don't like, and then
with people that you're close to. So,
your family members,
people you're working with in whichever
of the 41 organizations you're in, okay?
People you're close to.
Uh then he says pa ma.
Yeah, mother and father. I won't repeat
the famous exam I had.
Uh
Okay, I was trying to learn Tibetan I
was trying to get into a Tibetan class,
and you had to do a oral interview to
get into the class, and you had to know
some Tibetan.
And my lama my one of my teachers wanted
me to get in.
And I would just started Tibetan like
last week and
and he let me come into the exam. And he
And there's this big big geshe in there
and and he
and my teacher said, uh okay, we're
going to ask you some Tibetan words.
If you can give them to us, you can join
the class. The class was Shantideva, by
the way.
50 years ago. And uh
he said, you ready? And I said, yeah.
And he said, pa ma.
And I'm like,
dad and mom, he says pass.
So pa ma means your parents, okay?
Uh they're important lo jong objects,
okay? Uh be careful around your parents.
Uh shak ro means
roommates,
okay? Shak is the Tibetan word for
especially for a monk's
quarters, okay? So roommates, people who
are in the same
uh
group of mo
monk cells in the monastery, okay?
Shak ro tabun surdukul surdukul
Tim, there's sur surkul.
Do you guys know surkul?
Uh
so
there's five great books in the Geshe
course. They take 25 years total.
You spend the first 12 years
in one book by Asanga, and that's the
one that Tim's translating. His book is
about
uh
it's about 3,000 pages in Tibetan,
which is uh 24,000 pages in English.
And he'll be an old man
by the time he finishes. Uh
and those uh commentaries to Maitreya
uh
perfection of wisdom, they are so huge
that
uh sometimes they have babies,
and they have uh surkuls. Surkul means
uh extracted topics. So you take special
topics and you extract them.
One of those extracted topics is the
wheel of life,
for example. In the original text,
it's the only one line,
uh okay? Uh
it's only a single line.
And then you take it out and you make a
whole 500-page book about it, okay? So,
that's called circle.
And here here you see it
uh used colloquially, which is one of
the great things about studying this
book, okay? You'll see circle used
in common language, okay?
And uh
you can go ahead and close that if you
need I I know you have a bad cold.
If you If you want to, okay.
Uh
So, circle means to take it out and
treat it separately, okay? Here it says
treat your parents,
treat your llama,
treat your roommates, treat your enemies
with special care, okay? Special when
you're doing lojong,
these people get special treatment,
okay? Take take them out of the other
people and they get special treatment,
either because they are high karmic
objects
or because you hate them.
Hopefully, there's nobody who's both.
All right.
All right. Uh next picture, you guys.
Tim, when do I have to shut up?
7:00?
7:15?
There's a countdown.
Oh, duh. Okay.
All right, cool. We'll do Q&A uh in the
last 15 minutes, okay? So, we'll stop in
about 15 minutes, okay? If you have
any kind of question, I don't care.
That's what the Geshe course is all
about. We learn to debate for 4 5 hours
a day.
So,
I like embarrassing difficult questions,
okay? So, feel free.
Okay. Mm.
Okay, next picture. Yeah, this guy.
That's
Dayang Senge Soktong Chenpo Zomma Zom
Lama Dupa Gom De.
Don't let your lojong practice be
affected by your personal circumstances.
If you're broke that week, your lojong
should be rich.
If you're rich that week, although your
lojong should be
your lojong should be rich, okay? So,
your lojong is rich
no matter
you know, you got money this week or you
don't have money this week. By the way,
as an old man, I'll tell you
as soon as you think you have money, it
goes away.
And
and every time you think you don't have
money, some comes.
So, don't get too worried about it. Just
keep your lojong standing, okay? And
don't worry
you know, either you die or you'll get
some money. So, either way, it doesn't
matter.
Okay. Uh then he has a quotation. I love
to find quotations.
I couldn't find it. I I it may be just
uh
some oral tradition or something, okay?
Dodang nyima trödze chöbe zuk
kyen-ngän tok-pa se tam-älwa
shib-tab-älma songwa.
Uh Dodang means if your belly is full
okay?
Nyima trödze means and when you're
sitting in the sun on a cool day
it means when things are going well.
Your belly's full
and you're and the sun comes out on a
cloudy day.
Chöbe zuk means you look like a
practitioner.
And then
chö means Dharma, chöba means
practitioner, okay? Dharma person.
Then kyen-ngän tok-pa se
when some crap comes up in your life
suddenly
tam-älwa, you lose your
your spiritual appearance, you know? And
then you're like, "Ah, shit."
You know? Okay, it says be like that,
okay?
Don't be happy when stuff's going well,
it never lasts.
And don't freak out when stuff messes up
cuz that doesn't last either, okay? Just
when you've been in the
Dharma business for 50 years, you'll
figure it out.
You know,
it bad times don't last forever. We had
terrible times here.
And good times don't last forever, just
keep it steady.
Lojong means keep it steady. Keep a
steady sweet attitude towards everybody
cuz the bad stuff will pass
and the good stuff will pass. So, just
stay steady.
Dawa Masala Rinpoche.
Uh he says the reason you are sitting
here in a Lamrim class is to learn
something higher
and don't drag the Dharma down to your
daily business, okay? Like keep it
higher. Let the Dharma stay higher.
Don't
don't turn Dharma into a business. Don't
turn it into a
a day-to-day
thing, okay? Let it stay high.
Keep it high, okay? Uh
use it for
to help people and don't use it for
making money or or or or lower purposes,
okay?
It's not that it's a bad karma or
something like that. It's just not
it's like putting the king in in a
pink tennis shoes or something, you
know? It's just not appropriate. It
doesn't look nice.
Okay? Can you imagine King Charles in in
pink tennis shoes or something? I Well,
maybe him.
Uh
but uh
you know,
don't use the high Dharma in some kind
of stupid to make some money or
something. It's not it doesn't fit, you
know, okay?
All right. Uh,
then he has a famous
uh, there's a famous little
in that box. You guys, can you scroll up
a little bit? Yeah.
Uh, next life rather than this one,
Dharma rather than world, feeling
towards others rather than the book.
Okay.
This is a famous
Lamrim
maxim, okay?
These
are the three
maxims of the Lojong practice, okay?
Number one,
uh,
you won't have trouble
using Dharma for this life,
like to make money or something. You
won't have trouble with this problem
if you don't think about this life,
okay? If you're focused on your next
life,
if you're focused on what happens in the
big picture,
uh, you won't
you won't
sell Dharma or something cuz cuz this
life
money is for this life.
Okay? Whatever money you happen to
collect in this life is canceled when
you take your last breath,
okay? And it and it doesn't matter to
anybody anymore, okay? So,
if your focus is on is a bigger focus,
you know, like I got a a million
lifetimes I got to work, you know, I got
to help people for a million lifetimes,
then you're not going to be so worried
about one little 100-year period,
you know? You're not going to think so
much about it. And then you it won't
even
occur to you to try to collect money
during uh this 50 years or 25 years you
have left, you know? What's the point?
You know, you got billions of lifetimes
to work on. So, what's the point of
trying to collect a few hundred dollars
more although I'm not kidding.
Uh
next lifetime, so
if you're focused on
all your lifetimes, you won't have this
problem of uh
taking money too seriously cuz it's it's
going to leave you anyway. There's a
joke in Tibetan.
Yeah, the money will have to look for a
new owner, you know?
Oh, Stanley died, really?
Where's his bank account going to go?
I don't know. It'll have to look for
somebody uh
you know, bank accounts are always
losing their
owners.
You don't think about it. Bank accounts
are lonely people.
They have to go look for new owners
every couple years, you know?
So,
okay. So, if your focus is on
all your lifetimes, then you're not
going to
take it so seriously about the money in
this life and stuff like that. Then you
will not tend to corrupt the Dharma
and use it for something in this life,
okay?
Secondly, uh Dharma rather than the
world means if your face I have this
every morning. Every morning
I feel like a cute girl in high school.
Uh people attack my
I don't want to say virginity, but
people attack my time.
People want my practice time. Really,
seriously attack.
Like terrible attacks and not very nice
sometimes. And they're they're like,
"You got to meet with me right now."
And I'm like, "This is my practice time.
I'm sorry. I don't do anything till
11:00."
You know, and then I get these vicious
attacks and on my time, and I'm like,
"Okay, you know, I don't care. Pull out
as many hairs as you want. Just At this
point, it doesn't matter.
You know, so
So, you got to protect your practice
time, okay? And don't let people
You're not helping anybody
when you give up your practice time,
okay? Keep your practice time.
I I just tell people, 11:01,
my my peacock door is open.
You know, you can come and ask me to
fundraise, and
you can repeat your complaints about
your partner for the 10,000th time, and
and I'm open, you know? But, uh
But, until then, it's Dharma, you know?
And I'm not open. Okay? So, I think you
got to
be brave and stubborn,
and you got to protect your practice
time, okay? And I'm I'm a hard-ass about
it. I really am.
And I don't see people before 11:00
unless they're dying, and then I kind of
flip a coin.
Uh
Okay, last one. Uh
He says, "Lamrim and Lojong
is not a book.
It's a feeling, okay? Lamrim is not in a
book.
Lojong is not in a book.
Uh it's a feeling in your heart, okay?
So, if you're looking for Lojong,
uh
it's not so much in a book. It's a
feeling inside of your heart, okay?
That's what he says. All right. Mm,
I still have time.
Send Dilyak Khyentse
Lojong Gompa Tsorchok Gope Yinsu. Okay,
we covered that.
Uh we're going back to the Lojong
Dondunma, which is the seven-point
Lojong that was kept secret for at least
300 years, 400 years, and probably
longer. Some of the Lojong masters
claimed that Lord Buddha started the
Lojong and kept it secret. So, that
would make it 2 and 1/2 thousand years
old.
But, um we're going back to the to the
Lojong Dondunma, okay? And he's giving
little hints about how to practice
Lojong for the rest of your life.
We're like towards the end of the Lojong
Dondunma. Then, we're going to start the
six perfections, okay?
Uh
Now that we have
bodhicitta, we can start the six
perfections, okay? Now that we have the
the wish for enlightenment, we can start
the six perfections, okay?
So, uh he says, "Kolok mijak." Say,
"Kolok."
Kolok.
There's two goloks. There's a golok in
Tibetan, which is a really weird
warrior caste from East Tibet. They talk
Do you want funny talk? They talk really
funny.
And so, this is a old warrior caste in
East Tibet. But, this kolok
different pronunciation, kolok means uh
don't do ass backwards.
Okay, ass backwards means uh
totally opposite, okay? And I'm
Lojong is supposed to be funny
and colloquial. So, I can use bad
language during Lojong, okay? And
but I don't mind if you don't tell my
wife. Uh so, kolok means uh
don't practice ass backwards, you know?
Don't get things backwards, okay? Don't
do it backwards, okay? That's Chekhawa's
advice, right?
Chekhawa didn't write it, he released it
to the public.
Okay? Um
around 1100 something.
Kolok gya cha
Uh then he says kolok truk.
Uh what's truk?
Six session
yoga practice, right? Uh so here
uh
lok truk means six as backwards.
Six as backward practices, okay? There's
six ways you can get it backwards, okay?
Six different ways. Kolok gya cha means
here's six different ways I don't want
you to get it backwards, okay?
So here we go.
This is where they they snip out uh
Geshe la's talk when I say, "Don't do
this, do the opposite." And then they
cut out the do the opposite part and
they put it and posted online.
You know, Geshe la says, "You know,
don't mess around with your friend's
wife." And then they cut out the
"don't"
Then I like, "Mess around with your
friend's wife." And
anyway,
uh chiky ja wa la
nying rü ka che mi söl
pa chi ten kyi ja wa la ka che si
Söl pa.
Kolok.
What's söl pa mean?
Patience, okay? Uh patience.
But it has a lot of other meanings,
okay? So patience usually means not to
get upset with somebody.
Uh
but it also means to be able to do an
extended task without getting
frustrated.
Right? So be patient, it's going to be
over
next Monday.
You'll be on the plane happy with the
refreshments.
Those massive refreshments
they give you.
Uh so super means uh
super means uh don't lose heart.
Don't lose
don't lose your spirit, okay? So kawat
kawat kawat means difficulty, okay? When
you have trouble
uh with your lojong practice.
Uh in English you say grin and bear it,
it means
okay, hit me again.
Hit me again. Hit me again, you know?
And you're like and life keeps hitting
you and you're like
hit me again, you
So kawat che it means uh
be a tough guy.
Be a tough guy, okay? Life will keep
hitting you and then you know, you get a
big smash in your face and
you lose all your money in the morning
and then then you're like
okay, hit me again, you know? And then
you get a bill for something that you
didn't buy.
You know, in the afternoon. In the
morning you lose all your money.
In the afternoon they hit you again with
this bill, you know? And
kawat kawat
super kawat means
be
uh be a tough guy about the right
things.
Be a tough guy about the right things.
So some people
they'll be a tough guy about stupid
stuff like fixing a car.
You know, I've done I fixed the car once
for like 8 months.
And that's also called super. That's
also called
what do you putting up with it? You put
up with it for 8 months fixing this
stupid
aluminum block Volkswagen Bojito.
You know,
and that's a kind of super. That's a
kind of patience. That's a kind of
endurance.
And he says, that's colo.
That's ass backwards. That's not the
endurance we're talking about. We're not
talking about
trying to fix a car for 8 months. And
that's not lojong.
That's not lojong endurance. Lojong
endurance
is to I don't know
not get angry at your wife or husband
after 8 months of abuse, you know, and
you're just like
Okay, you know, like that's lojong.
That's real. That's supa.
Okay, that's patience.
You know, they hit you that I just I
mean
verbally they hit you and then they
you're like, okay honey.
Then
you're like, okay honey, you know.
And then 8 months of that you're like,
okay honey. Wait, I didn't say anything.
Okay, honey.
And you know, and uh
you know,
that's that's lojong.
Okay, it's not uh endurance
when you're
at work or something like that. It's
endurance emotionally.
It's endurance of your love for other
people and they keep attacking it and
you keep responding with love.
And that's that's real endurance, okay?
It's not endurance to
to do the accounting of ACI year after
year.
It is It is a kind of endurance, but
that's not lojong.
I I said exactly. Okay,
uh second We had six, right? We're
supposed to do six.
Uh let's start the other five tomorrow.
I'm sorry.
Later today, right? Am I right? Two
classes, right?
Okay, uh
Q&A. We need that big box. Please don't
hit anybody with the box. I just I get
nervous when you guys throw it around.
Geshe-la,
I have a question.
Good.
We were here in
October
and uh
the the other the second war started. We
had already the first one.
We are here in April.
The third war started.
Is there a third one? I don't know.
But we'll we'll keep our patience.
Uh
Iran attacked Israel yesterday.
Or does
Does it work?
Okay.
So, uh how we can use uh our time
wisely?
Ready?
How we can use our time here wisely, you
know, to
Maybe you have suggestions that we
cannot think about.
Okay, good.
Yeah, I'll repeat it. It seems like uh
every time we have a long room retreat
here and there's a new war breaks out.
And uh
what can we do or or how can we think
about it and like that or something like
that? I I don't think um
I I don't think in this case that we are
purifying
our old bad karma because uh
we're doing such a good thing. You see
what I mean? Sometimes
when you do something really good,
it burns off the crap of some old bad
thing you did, you know? So, sometimes
when you do a really good thing,
uh it it wakes up bad seeds from the
past and some disaster happens to you.
Uh I don't think it's that kind of
thing.
Uh
in this case, I think it's um just
generally
that I
I would say this. I mean, um
I grew up
in 100 years ago.
Uh
my dad had served in World War II.
And uh
and he was
he and my wife's father were alcoholics
and messed up, really seriously messed
up. And from the war, they saw war when
they were
18, 19 years old. And they they never
got over it.
And uh
and that was 100 million people died.
100 million people died. And so, um
I mean, if you're a Buddha looking over
this planet right now, uh you we have
the
potential
to kill billions of people in the next
few days with something. It can happen.
Uh
but in general,
uh
we're making some progress. And I think
we don't think about it much, you know.
For example, with starvation,
uh
when I was a kid, it was serious problem
in India, for example. Uh
And and millions of people were dying.
And uh now because of
partly because of computerization of
distribution,
uh
there's almost no starvation
except for war. When there's a war, you
know, they can't get food to people. But
uh in general,
uh
the planet is holding steady, I think.
And uh if you look at it from an old
man's viewpoint,
you know, things are messed up. And uh
there's a lot for us to do.
But I think also you have to think about
the progress and and the things have
the lojong still exists, the lamrim
still exists. You know, there's a lot of
beautiful things going on. So, I think
you have to be a peacock.
And you have to stick your nose into it.
And I was tempted not to, you know. I
was like, you know, okay, all my
Ukrainian friends need some help.
I'm busy, you know. So, we brought two
people and it was hard. It's really
hard. Financially, it's hard.
And um
so uh
you know, stick your nose in and and
help.
My brother went to Poland and made
sandwiches. He made 300,000 sandwiches.
Uh
with the World Food Kitchen.
and then his supervisor was killed uh
last week
in in Gaza. And uh
so uh
you know, you if you're practicing load
zone
uh
do do
step up, do something,
help somebody.
And if we all do that, we'll be okay.
And and the problems are huge.
You know, thousands and thousands of
people dying and I I don't think
personally, I don't think it helps to
to try to
to think about how can I stop 10,000
people from dying or something like
that. Let me help one or two people.
Uh with with my income and help them and
and then if we all do that
uh I think we can improve things. So, I
you know,
there's a famous story, okay?
Uh
every billion years or so
this planet
melts.
Okay? Every billion years or so there's
an atomic war on this particular planet.
And uh the whole earth is covered in
fire and all human beings die. All all
life dies.
And
then there's a supposedly there's a god
realm
up above us, you know, form realm,
formless realm,
desire realm gods. And the young ones
who are only 800,000 years old,
they say, "Well, look, the earth is
burning, you know, it's covered in
fire." And then the older deities, the
gods, they say, "Ah,
they blow themselves up every billion
years or so.
Don't worry about it.
It just goes over and over again, you
know, it's like you know."
So, I think uh
when you get to my age and you've seen
it so many times and
you you
you just quietly work against it.
And you can't get too freaked out. You
can't
you can't let the fact that there's so
much violence uh
freak you out. You have to I was in
Vietnam.
Uh
I was supposed to fight in Vietnam. I
went to jail.
Uh
and uh
when you go there now, Mr. Bin and other
people are so so beautiful and friendly
to us and uh
you know, things change and uh
life life goes on and
so we just have to keep uh
doing what we can do to help.
Uh but I think if you worry about the
whole, you know, millions of people,
don't go crazy about it, you know. Lo
Jong means start with the people around
you help. Do what you can do.
Do to the best of your ability and and
don't get
overwhelmed by
the the the war in this planet is
nothing compared to the war going on
in a billion planet, you know. So, you
can't
you can't let it get you down. You got
to
you got to be a peacock today.
And if enough people stand up to be
peacocks, it'll just be
I did a retreat in Flagstaff. Veronica
found me a cabin.
A nice cabin out in the woods.
And
I sat down, you know, to do a three-week
retreat and um
and then THERE'S THIS LIKE
AND THEN LIKE A THOUSAND VOICES.
And I'm like, what's that, you know? And
I asked the owner, what's that noise?
They said they have a peacock farm next
door.
I'm like, I'm doing a three year three
week retreat here. I'm sorry, you can't
you can't tell the peacocks to shut up.
And
so anyway,
you just do your retreat the best you
can and
the peacock Okay. All right, one more
question. Tim, something?
And so this is a question from online.
And it says, dear dearest Geshe La,
that's too high.
If I don't want to live billions and
billions of years, I want to speed this
up as fast as possible.
How can I best use lojong to do that?
Mhm.
Yeah, if if I don't uh
want to go through billions of years of
suffering,
uh
how can I use lojong to get things
resolved quickly?
Uh
Again, I think it's like Ines' question.
I think you have to deal with what's
around you
and what's close to you. I I
use Lojong
he said in the text
focus your Lojong
on the high karmic objects around you.
Which means your teacher,
your enemies,
your close relatives, your roommates,
people you work with every day.
These are the peacock
uh objects of your practice, okay? It's
people you're around every day.
Uh
They're not very exciting. It's not very
glorious.
And that's where you have to start. Uh
you have to practice Lojong
with the difficult people in your own
life and and right around you. And and I
think if you have an intention
to overcome uh billions of years of
trouble,
uh you almost don't have a choice. You
have to start with the people right
around you. And uh
start with the high karmic objects
around you. And those are your people
you don't like.
And um
parents,
uh teachers,
uh roommates, and people you work with,
okay? Start with the people closest to
you. And don't worry about billions.
Start with four or five.
And
it What do you call it? It uh
there's repercussions in the billions of
people. Deal with the 10 people
you're closest to, and then the billions
will
will take care of it. When we do a fire
offering,
that's supposed to be the intention.
When the smoke
comes off the fire
and that fire is blessed,
then you have to
that night when we do the fire offering
here, hopefully we don't offer the whole
land on fire.
Uh
then you think about the smoke
going off into the
sky.
And sooner or later it will touch all
people in this world. Sooner or later
the rice you throw on the fire is going
to touch somebody in
Gaza and Ukraine and wherever else and
so that's the kind of
uh
motivation you can have when you are
practicing Lojong
with the people close to you. Sooner or
later that smoke will
touch all the people in the world. And
that's the only way we can touch all the
people in the world. So start with the
people nearby.